Hello, everyone, and welcome
to English Pod. My name is Marco.
My name is Katherine, and
today we're talking a little
bit about going to sleep
or not being able to sleep.
That's right, we are having some sleeping
problems, and that we're actually going to
check out a couple of words related to
this topic right now on vocabulary preview.
Very vocabulary preview. Okay,
so the first word is actually the
technical word that describes being
unable to sleep. It's called insomnia.
Right, so if you have
insomnia, it means
that you can't fall
asleep, you can't sleep.
Okay, so this is a pretty serious condition.
For example, if you have insomnia and you
don't sleep with three or four nights, you're
not going to do very well at work, right?
If you're studying,
you're tired at school, you
can't concentrate, so
it's a very big problem.
What's that other word
though? We have insomnia,
but we also have another
interesting disorder.
Right, if somebody is able
to sleep, but walks while
they're sleeping, that
person is called a sleep walker.
That's right, and you don't actually just
have to walk to be a sleep walker. You can do
any number of strange things like basically
acting like you're awake when you're not.
Exactly, so some people get up
and walk, actually go outside, some
people get dressed, some people
have to go downstairs and cook.
Yeah, that's right, and
the worst is the people who
eat because they gain weight
and they don't know why.
Exactly, so sleep walking
is what you do, and
if you do this, you're
called a sleep walker.
Okay, sleep walk is the verb sleep
walker is the noun or the person.
All right, so we've
taken a look at two words
that we're going to find
in our dialogue today.
Why don't we go now and listen
to the dialogue for the first time.
Alex, what's up with you?
You look dreadful.
Hey, Jill. I don't know. I've been having
trouble sleeping these past few weeks.
I usually lie in bed for
hours trying to get to sleep.
I've tried stretching and different
breathing techniques before going to bed.
I've tried eating and not eating different
foods. I've even tried counting sheep.
And then when I finally get to sleep, I
have these really disturbing nightmares,
so I usually wake up in a panic and
more tired than before I went to sleep.
Wow, maybe you should get that checked out.
Maybe you're stressed.
Just take some sedatives, works
for me. Every so often having
some melatonin on hand helps
me when I have trouble sleeping.
It works on all kinds
of sleeping disorders.
It's the stuff pilots use to
regular their sleeping patterns.
I heard of that, but does
that apply to Alex's situation?
Yeah, sure. Why not? Sounds
like he only has transient insomnia
since it's a recent thing, so taking
melatonin should do the trick.
But shouldn't he be looking
into why it's been happening?
Well, aren't you the little psychologist?
Our buddies having trouble sleeping.
It's easy and curable.
It's not something freakish,
like if he was a sleepwalker.
Well, there's that too.
All right, we're back so
obviously this person not only
has insomnia, but also has
nightmares, sleep walks of mess.
That's right, and you can tell when
someone hasn't been sleeping well.
They have that look like there's bags under
their eyes, or they just look really tired.
And so the friend here
says Alex, you look dreadful.
That's right, dreadful.
So this is an adjective and
it's a way to describe
someone that looks terrible.
You look horrible, you
look tired, you look sleepy.
That's right, so this
is not a compliment.
This is something that you say
when you're worried about someone.
So for example, if someone's really,
really tired, you say you look dreadful.
Or if someone is
wearing very dirty clothes,
they don't look like they
went home yesterday.
You say, "Oh, what's
wrong? You look dreadful.
" Right, I think you can also use it to
describe objects or maybe food, right?
This lasagna is dreadful.
It means it's very bad.
And you don't want to say that to
the person who cooked it, of course.
Exactly. All right, so
the person obviously
because is suffering from
insomnia looks dreadful.
And he was explaining what
he does to try to fall asleep.
For example, counting
sheep, stretching, and he also
said that he tried different
breathing techniques.
Okay, so basically a technique is an
approach to something, a kind of method.
But in this case, we're talking
about breathing techniques.
So for some people, one
breathing technique is breathing
in through your nose and
breathing out through your mouth.
Like that, that's one kind of technique.
So a technique, as you say,
is a way of doing something.
So breathing techniques are
different ways of breathing.
So maybe you will relax, so maybe
you'll fall asleep, things like this.
Exactly. It's one of
those things that you
might learn about in a
yoga class, for example.
There's different breathing techniques.
Right, and you can combine techniques
with other words, as well, adding the ING.
For example, you have walking techniques
maybe to put less stress on your knees.
Or running techniques, swimming techniques.
So I think there's a technique
for almost everything.
Just about anything you can
do, there's a technique for it.
Right, yeah, for sure.
All right, and while moving on, he
was talking about his nightmares.
And he described his
nightmares as disturbing.
He has disturbing nightmares.
Okay, well, I think this is an
important word to cover here,
Marco, because we've heard
the verb "too disturbed" before.
Like, I'm sorry to disturb you.
Means I'm sorry to bother you.
But disturbing is an adjective.
It describes something that
makes me very uncomfortable, right?
Right.
So, for example, a lot of
times in the news, we see
very disturbing images, car
accidents or fires or bombs.
And what's disturbing is when you
see human beings who have been hurt.
So, images that make you really
uncomfortable or sad, these are disturbing.
Exactly.
So disturbing nightmares are
nightmares that are not very pleasant.
They make him scared maybe.
You're uncomfortable.
Right, like a dream, for
example, where your parents die.
It's pretty disturbing.
Exactly.
All right, and well, one of his friends
recommended, you know what?
Stop with all of this.
Just take some sedatives.
Okay, so sedatives are
kind of medicine that help
a person relax or that
help make a person tired.
Right.
So, I think it comes
from the verb to sedate.
Yes.
And basically, that is to
calm down, to tranquilize.
That's right.
So, in this case, we're
talking about a person,
but you can also give
an animal sedatives.
For example, if you want to take your
dog on an airplane, the dog needs to relax.
You give it some sedatives.
Exactly.
And I think when he mentioned a specific
name of a sedative, it's melatonin.
That's right.
So, melatonin is a chemical that our bodies
naturally produce that help calm us down.
And so, a lot of
pharmaceutical companies or
drug companies sell
melatonin in a pill form.
It's basically, it's a chemical
that helps you relax.
Exactly.
So, obviously, if you take
melatonin, you're going
to feel sleepy or you're
going to be very relaxed,
and you're going to
fall asleep a lot easier.
Well, hopefully.
Hopefully.
That's right.
So, and, well, the
whole thing that we've
been talking about in some near sleepwalking,
these are called sleeping disorders.
Right.
Or you might also hear
the term sleep disorders.
They mean problems with sleeping.
So, people who either
cannot fall asleep or people
who have bad dreams
or people who sleepwalk.
Exactly.
Like, disorder is something of an
illness or a condition that is not normal.
So, for example, as you said,
a sleeping disorder or a sleep
disorder, it means that you're not
able to sleep properly or normally.
But there are other
kinds of disorders, right?
Right.
I guess many people have
heard of eating disorders.
Okay.
So, that's basically people who
do not eat like everyone else.
Exactly.
So, that's what happens with a disorder.
All right.
So, we've taken a look at a lot of vocab.
It's time for us to take a
look at fluency, builder, but
before that, why don't we
listen to the dialogue again?
Alex, what's up with you?
You look dreadful.
Hey, Jill.
I don't know.
I've been having trouble
sleeping these past few weeks.
I usually lie in bed for
hours trying to get to sleep.
I've tried stretching and different
breathing techniques before going to bed.
I've tried eating and
not eating different foods.
I've even tried counting sheep.
And then, when I finally get to sleep, I
have these really disturbing nightmares.
So, I usually wake up in a panic and
more tired than before I went to sleep.
Wow.
Maybe you should get that checked out.
Maybe you're stressed?
Just take some sedatives.
Works for me.
Every so often having some melatonin on
hand helps me when I have trouble sleeping.
It works on all kinds
of sleeping disorders.
It's the stuff pilots use to
regular their sleeping patterns.
I heard of that.
But does that apply to Alex's situation?
Yeah, sure.
Why not?
Sounds like he only
has transient insomnia
since it's a recent thing, so taking
melatonin should do the trick.
But shouldn't he be looking
into why it's been happening?
Well, aren't you the little psychologist?
Our buddies having trouble sleeping.
It's easy and curable.
It's not something freakish
like if he was a sleepwalker.
Well, there's that too.
Alright, we're back.
So now we have three main
phrases for fluency builder.
Why don't we start with the first one?
Okay, so you heard in today's
dialogue an interesting phrase.
I don't know if it exists
in other languages, but
in English we say when
you're trying to fall
asleep, there's a good
technique to help you do so.
You count sheep.
Yeah, I think you see it
in cartoons all the time.
A person is sleeping
and over that cartoon's
head is a little cloud and you see
sheep jumping over a fence, right?
So yeah, basically there's a
fence and you say one, two, three.
And the process of
counting helps relax a person.
Then you fall asleep.
Right.
So counting sheep, I guess you're not
literally out in a field counting sheep.
You're just imagining sheep in your
head and you're trying to fall asleep.
That's right.
Counting sheep.
All right, and well,
one of his friends
recommended that maybe
he should go to a doctor
and Jill said that by saying maybe
you should get that checked out.
Okay, so to get something
checked out, to get it
checked out, this means
to have a professional
give you a suggestion or to have
a professional look at something.
Exactly.
So maybe you should get examined.
Maybe you should go to the doctor.
This isn't just about disorders, right?
I mean, what if I have a sore tooth?
I could say this.
Right.
So if you have a toothache,
I would recommend,
oh, maybe you should get
that checked out by my dentist.
Right.
Or maybe if you have a bad rash,
you know, your skin is very red.
And say Marco, I think you should
get that checked out by a doctor.
Exactly.
So to get something
checked, to get something
examined by a doctor
or a professional.
All right, and the last
phrase that we have for you.
So last phrase we have today
comes from a suggestion at the end.
The friend suggests taking melatonin.
And he says, listen, taking
melatonin should do the trick.
Right.
So if you end a phrase by
saying that should do the trick.
Basically you're saying that
should solve your problem.
That should help you.
Exactly.
So the trick you don't have
to think about what the trick is.
It's just a way of saying
it should fix your problem.
So for example, when someone is fixing
my car and they have one more thing to do.
And it's finished.
She says the car mechanic
might say, that should do the trick.
Right.
That means problem solved.
Or maybe you're having, you
want to hang a picture on your wall.
So somebody puts a nail in the
wall and that should do the trick.
And maybe that'll hold up the painting.
Done.
That's a way of saying that
should solve the problem.
This should be the solution.
That should be all.
Okay.
So why don't we go back and
listen to the dialogue one last time.
Alex, what's up with you?
You look dreadful.
Hey, Joe.
I don't know.
I've been having trouble
sleeping these past few weeks.
I usually lie in bed for
hours trying to get to sleep.
I've tried stretching and different
breathing techniques before going to bed.
I've tried eating and
not eating different foods.
I've even tried counting sheep.
And then when I finally get to sleep, I
have these really disturbing nightmares.
So I usually wake up in a panic and
more tired than before I went to sleep.
Wow.
Maybe you should get that checked out.
Maybe you're stressed.
Just take some sedatives.
Works for me.
Every so often having some melatonin on
hand helps me when I have trouble sleeping.
It works on all kinds
of sleeping disorders.
It's the stuff pilots use to
regular their sleeping patterns.
I heard of that.
But does that apply to Alex's situation?
Yeah, sure.
Why not?
Sounds like he only has transient
insomnia since it's a recent thing.
So taking melatonin should do the trick.
But shouldn't he be looking
into why it's been happening?
Well, aren't you the little psychologist?
Everybody's having trouble sleeping.
It's easy and curable.
It's not something freakish
like if he was a sleepwalker.
Well, there's that too.
All right, we're back.
So talking about dreaming
nightmares and insomnia, all of this.
What do you do if you can't fall asleep?
I don't really have this
problem, personally.
Because I could fall
asleep anywhere, anywhere.
I've heard some people take
more milk before going to sleep.
Yes, some people take milk.
Although I also heard
that dairy products
before bedtime can
make you have nightmares.
I really need cheese before bed.
I've heard that as well.
I've heard that if you
have seafood before bed.
You'll have nightmares as well.
But actually, have you ever
had a dream when you are
doing something and you
wake up in the middle of that?
Yes.
I remember once I was
dreaming, I was drinking a soda.
And all of a sudden, I woke up
and I had my head like in the air.
Doing the action of me
actually drinking the soda.
Actually, sometimes this happens
to me when I'm falling asleep.
I imagine I'm on a bike or something
and I start to feel myself moving my leg.
And I wake up and I'm like,
wait, wait, what am I doing?
So the brain is very strange.
I think, especially in
those times when you're
kind of asleep and
you're kind of awake.
Also, when you wake up suddenly, I don't
know if other people have experienced this.
But you feel like you're
falling or something.
Obviously, you just wake up with a shake.
Yeah, your body moves.
Yeah, it's really scary.
It's very scary.
Your heart starts to beat.
I don't know why that happens, though.
It's unusual.
Well, we're curious to know
what your sleep habits are.
Do you have a hard time
sleeping or are you like me?
It's very easy for you to fall asleep.
Let us know at our website, EnglishPod.com.
Alright, we'll see you guys there. Bye.